Hi Fox, today's video is going to be very
interesting and important
for every person who has a health
insurance policy. Fox,
one thing is common in all of us human beings that we
never want to get sick and neither do we
ever want that we or
any member of our family should ever get admitted in the hospital,
but one thing we all want is that if there is ever
any hospitalization, then the
expenses of that hospitalization should
not be heavy on our pocket, that is, the claim of
that hospitalization should be settled through our health insurance policy
and the most important thing is that the claim should be
settled hassle-free.
Fox, you will think that why do I emphasize
hassle-free claim settlement in every video of mine.
Fox, insurance
companies find an excuse to reject your health insurance claim
because the
owner of the insurance company has
opened the insurance company to earn profit and not to give you a claim,
but if you know the correct claim settlement
process, are aware of it and your
claim is filed as per the terms and conditions of your health insurance policy, then the
company will settle your claim.  If you ca
n't reject it, it's very important for you to know the claim settlement process for a hassle-free claim
settlement. So,
in today's video, I've brought to you the
claim settlement process of the six most popular health insurance companies in our country.
So, stay tuned to my video till the
end. If you have
n't subscribed to the insurance service yet, then
subscribe now and press the bell icon.
Also, share this video with
your friends and relatives
because this information is very important for everyone.
[Music]
Those six health insurance companies are:
number one HDFC Ergo General Insurance
Company, number two ICICI Lombard General Insurance
Company, number three TA AIG General
Insurance Company, number four Niva Bupa
Health Insurance Company, number five Care Health Insurance Company,
and number six Star
Health & Allied Insurance Company Limited.
So, first of all, I'll talk about the
documentation. What documents will we need for the claim settlement
process or for filing a claim? These are almost the same
for all companies. First of all,
we need  There is a
detailed discharge summary. Discharge summary is a
document in which the entire history of the patient is
written. Why was the patient
admitted? What were his applications?
What were his symptoms? What was the treatment given to him?
What is his past history? And
in what condition was he discharged?
This is called discharge summary, which is a mandate
document for settling any health insurance
claim. Second is the
final hospital bill. Hospital
final bill means what were your expenses in the hospital? How much was the
room rent? How much were the
ICU charges?
How much were the medicines spent? What were the expenses of your other tests, etc.,
diagnostics, etc.
Third is the payment receipt, that is, the
receipt of the payment you made against that bill will be
required. Fourth document will be
your reports along with bills of all your diagnostic lab
tests, blood tests, X-rays, ECG, PET scans,
ultrasounds.
Apart from that, you need KYC documents.
Aadhar card, PAN card, a
cancelled cheque with your name printed on it.  It
should have happened and a photo of you is also required
for the claim settlement process.
Some claims also require an indoor case paper.
Indoor case paper
means we can also call it a progress report.
You must have seen that
whenever a doctor comes to see a patient in a hospital,
whenever he visits him, the
doctor shares his progress report with his
attendant and the attendant keeps a note of all those
progress reports on a paper.
This is called indoor case paper. The
doctor's note contains details of the
patient's condition when he was admitted,
whether he was
given treatment and how he
progressed during that treatment, as well as
his past history.
In some cases, an MLC report, such as
in accident cases or in cases
where there is third-party involvement, an
MLC or FIR report is also
required. So these are all the
documents that
we will need for any claim settlement process. Now let us discuss the
different types of these companies.
How are the different claim settlement processes? First of all, I will
talk about what is the
claim settlement process of HDFC RGO General Insurance Company. So,
we will first talk about the cashless claim process of SDFC Ergo General Insurance Company.
Their cashless time is
30 minutes for initial approval and four
hours for final approval. Talking about the
reimbursement claim process, the reimbursement
claim process of HDFC Ergo will be
fully online. Here,
after getting admitted in the hospital, you have to
intimate the insurance company within 48 hours. You will have to
get the intimation number from there. After that,
you have to file all the documents online
or send them by email to care@adacrgo.com
and your claim is going to be settled.
Talking about III Lord,
III Lord's claim settlement
process is also very smooth. Their cashless
time is just one hour, that is, within 1 hour, they give
their initial approval as well as
their final approval.  The approval is also approved. Let's
talk about the reimbursement
claim process. ICICI Lord's
reimbursement claim process will also be fully
online. They have an app, the link of which
I will provide in your description.
You have to go to that link and upload all the documents.
After uploading all those documents, your claim gets settled within 48
days if no query is raised in it.
If any query is raised, then
after replying to that query,
your claim gets settled within 3 to 4 days. Let's
talk about Tata AIG's
claim settlement process. First of all,
we will talk about the cashless claim process.
Tata AIG's cashless claim process has a maximum delay of
48 hours, which is an industry standard claim settlement process. Let's talk about the reimbursement claim process. In Tata AIG, you will first have to intimate the insurance company within 48 hours of being admitted to the hospital.  You will need to
obtain an intimation number, and
after obtaining that number, you will need to
process all the documents online.
Tata Easy's reimbursement claim process will be fully
online. Similarly,
your claim will be settled within three to four days
if no query is raised.
If a query is raised, the same amount of
time will be extended.
After replying to the query, your claim will be settled within three to four days. Let's
talk about Niva
Bupa Health Insurance Company's claim
settlement process. Niva
Bupa's cashless claim settlement process takes
30 minutes for initial approval. This means that
after being admitted to the hospital,
they will give you their decision within 30 minutes, either
rejecting the claim or approving it. At the
time of discharge,
they settle your claim within a maximum of four hours. Let's
talk about Niva Bupa
's reimbursement  Regarding the claim process, the
reimbursement claim process of Niva Bupa is
fully online. There is a link for this too, which
I will give you in the description.
You have to go to that link and upload all the documents one by one
and after that
your claim gets settled within three to four or five days
if no query is raised in it
and as soon as any query is
raised, after replying to that query,
your claim gets settled within three to four days.
See, I am telling you in every claim
that the claim gets settled within three to four days
but its
maximum is 30 days but generally
insurance companies settle the claim in three to four days
if no
query is raised in it or the company does not have
any kind of doubt. So let me talk about
Care Health Insurance. Let us talk about the
claim settlement process of Care Health Insurance.
So first of all,
cashless claim, the time for cashless claim of Care Health Insurance is
4 hours. Within
these four hours, the insurance company settles its
In Care
Health Insurance, you have to
submit the reimbursement claim online and
also send the hard copies to their head office.
In Care Health Insurance, it is mandatory to
intimate the insurance company within 48 hours.
After that, you have to
process all the documents online by
going to their link; I will provide that link
in the description. After that,
you have to courier all the documents to their head
office in Gurgaon. Talking about the
claim settlement process of Star Health and Elite, if we
talk about their claim settlement process in cashless, then within 48
hours they have to settle or
reject the claim.
However, in the case of reimbursement, their claim
settlement process is comparatively tough
because their claim settlement process
is completely offline. First, you have to
intimate the insurance company within 24 hours
and get an intimation number from there.
After getting that intimation number, all the
documents have to be couriered to their head office in Chennai.  This has to be done
within 15 days from the
discharge date. If you do not send all these documents to the head office within 50 days or 15 days from the
discharge date,
your claim may be
rejected. And if you do
not make claim intimation within 24 hours,
your claim may also be rejected. Fox
SDF Sir, the general insurance company has
taken another initiative. To make its services even better,
it has published a
list of early discharge hospitals.
It has made a
special tie-up with some hospitals. According to that tie-up,
if a patient is
admitted in its hospital, an initial approval will be
taken and the
patient will not be made to wait for the final approval. As soon as the
doctor asks for discharge, he will be
discharged immediately without
final approval. This is called a
discharge hospital network list. Fox
Now I will talk about which types of claims
trigger investigation by insurance companies. The first one is
early claim. Early claim means that if
in the first year itself any  If a claim has been made, then the
insurance companies
can trigger an investigation in it that the
insurance
companies will settle your claim only after it is pre-established, otherwise
your insurance companies can reject the claim, the
second one happens
in case of an accident or in such a case where there is
involvement of a third party like gun
shot, in this accident case the insurance
companies justify that whether the
insured was under alcohol influence during the accident
or whether any
criminal activity was taking place due to which that
accident happened, I will
tell you my personal experience,
a few years ago we had a case of gun shot, in that the
insurance companies made a lot of
queries, they
asked for the FIR report, asked for the MLC report, did the
entire investigation, the insurance company
wanted to know whether there was any
intentional act in it or whether there was any
old rivalry going on due to which
this gun shot happened or whether the insured was involved in any other
criminal activity,
everything was completely investigated  The
insurance
company settled the claim only after a thorough investigation and being completely satisfied.
I get a lot of queries from you regarding the fake claim settlement process, a lot of
phone calls, a lot of mails.
I have tried in this video to
answer all your mails, to
resolve all your queries, but
still, if you have some more questions, some
queries, then you can ask me, you can also
mail me in my comment box,
you can also call me.
Do let me know how you liked this video. I will
meet you in my next
video, till then Jai
Hind.